Authors Collection, 1845-1986
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Authors Collection
1845-1986
MS 443
12 boxes; 4 volumes (4.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The Authors Collection contains small amounts of material on a number of women writers from the U.S. and abroad. Types of materials include biographical writings, articles, reviews, newspaper clippings, and other printed materials. There are also some letters, manuscripts and photographs. A large portion of the collection relates to author Margaret Mitchell, and her book and the movie, Gone With the Wind. Other authors represented include Louisa May Alcott, Elizabeth Barrett Browning, Willa Cather, Doris Lilly, Emily Dickinson, Edna St. Vincent Millay, Tillie Olsen, Harriet Beecher Stowe, and Virginia Woolf.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Authors Collection is comprised of bibliographies of women writers, both from the U.S. and abroad; general files on women authors by country; and files on individual authors and poets. In a few cases there are typescripts of an author's works, photographs, biographical information, newspaper clippings, and some reviews. The collection dates approximately from 1845 to 1976. Individual authors represented include Louisa May Alcott, Elizabeth Barrett Browning, Willa Cather, Emily Dickinson, Edna St. Vincent Millay, Tillie Olsen, Harriet Beecher Stowe, and Virginia Woolf, among others. There is one complete manuscript, How to Make Love to a Man in Five Languages, by Doris Lilly. A substantial section on Margaret Mitchell includes newspaper clippings, magazine articles, and correspondence about Mitchell, the publication of Gone With the Wind, the release of the movie, and efforts of the Atlanta Smith Club to raise money for Margaret Mitchell scholarships to send Georgia women to Smith. Correspondence includes letters from Mitchell to Julia Collier Harris and her husband Julian Harris (circa 1936-47), both newspaper editors who, together, received the Pulitzer Prize in journalism for their editorials in the Columbus (Georgia) Enquirer-Sun against the Ku Klux Klan.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into four series:
I. GENERAL
II. COUNTRIES
III. INDIVIDUAL AUTHORS
IV. POETRY
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to the collection are expected and may not be reflected in this finding aid..
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors. Portions of the Margaret Mitchell materials were purchased and presented to the Sophia Smith Collection by Frank Neely and Rachel Schlesinger Neely (Smith class 1907).
Search Terms
Baldwin, James, 1924-1987; Lorde, Audre; Mitchell, Margaret, 1900-1949--Correspondence; Authors--Biography--Sources; Women authors--Biography--Sources
- SERIES I. GENERAL
  - Bibliographies
    - "Women Writers" (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Neglected American Women Writers" (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Women and Literature" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Digging Out: Lost Voice of New England Women Writers (New England Women Writers Project)1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous articles and fliers on women authors (Box 1, Folder 4)
- SERIES II. COUNTRIES
  - General: clippings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Canada (Box 1a, Folder 1)
  - England
    - General (Box 1a, Folder 2)
    - Berners, Dame Juliana (Box 1a, Folder 3)
    - Carroll, Lewis: "The Real Alice" (Box 1a, Folder 4)
  - France
    - Beauvoir, Simone de (Box 1a, Folder 5)
    - de Staël, Madame (Box 1a, Folder 6)
    - Collette, Sidonie Gabrielle (Box 1a, Folder 7)
    - Sand, George (Box 1a, Folder 8)
  - Germany (Box 1a, Folder 9)
  - Italy (Box 1a, Folder 10)
  - Netherlands (Box 1a, Folder 11)
  - Japan (Box 1a, Folder 12)
  - Norway (Box 1a, Folder 13)
  - Portugal: Margarida Ofelia Avelar de Carvalho (Box 1a, Folder 14)
  - Spain (Box 1a, Folder 15)
  - Sweden: Selma Lagerlöf (Box 1a, Folder 16)
- SERIES III. INDIVIDUAL AUTHORS
  - Adams, Hannah (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alcott, Louisa May
    - General (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Louisa M. Alcott, Her Life, Letters and Journals, edited by Ednah D. Cheney (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Alexander, Francesca (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Allinson, Anne C.E. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Baldwin, Faith (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Barr, Amelia E. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bates, Katherine Lee (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bottome, Phyllis (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bowen, Catherine Drinker (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Brachen, Peg (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bradstreet, Anne (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Brontë;, Charlotte and family (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Browning, Elizabeth Barrett and Penini (son) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Buck, Pearl S. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Burnett, Constance Buell (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Cary, Alice and Phoebe (Box 2a, Folder 1)
  - Cather, Willa S.
    - General and photograph (Box 2a, Folder 2)
    - Willa Cather Pioneer Memorial Newsletters 1962-76 (Box 2a, Folder 2a)
  - Cheney, Ednah Dow (Box 2a, Folder 3)
  - Child, Lydia Maria: correspondence, clippings, and Letters from New York1845 (Box 2a, Folder 4)
  - Cleghorn, Sarah N. (Box 2a, Folder 5)
  - Converse, Florence (Box 2a, Folder 6)
  - Creevey, Caroline Althea (Box 2a, Folder 6a)
  - d'Arona, Florence Roosevelt: photograph (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - De la Ramée, Louisa (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dickinson, Emily (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Diver, Maud
    - Bibliography (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Letters (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Illustration for Royal India (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dodge, Mary Mapes (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Dorr, Julia Caroline Ripley (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Elliot, George (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Evans, Anne, [see also book on shelf] (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Fairfield, Genevra (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Fisher, Dorothy Canfield (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Fry, Anne (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Fuller, Carol: typed copy of Vestal Flame (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Fuller, Margaret (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Gale, Zona (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Gardener, Helen Hamilton (Alice Chenowith Day) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Gardner, Isabella Stewart (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Genlis, Felicite Ducrest Contesse de (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hale, Sarah Josepha Buell (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hall, Evelyn Beatrice (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Hamilton, Edith (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Harper, Frances E.W. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Hobart, Alice Tisdale (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Lilly, Doris: How to Make Love in Five Different Languages (manuscript) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Jackson, Helen Hunt (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Jewett, Sarah Orne (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Larcom, Lucy
    - General (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - A New England Girlhood 1890 (Box 5, Folder 3a)
  - Lazarus, Emma (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Leitch, Mary Sinton (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Lerner, Gerda (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Levertov, Denise (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lilly, Doris, [see box 4]
  - Lorde, Audre, [see box 10]
  - Lowell, Amy (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Macaulay, Catharine (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Macaulay, Rose: letter to M. Nicolson (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Martineau, Harriet (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Millay, Edna St. Vincent (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Mitchell, Margaret, [see box 9]
  - Mitchison, Naomi (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Mitford, Mary Russel (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Moore, Julia A. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Norris, Kathleen (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - O'Conner, Flannery (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Olsen, Tillie (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Ostenso, Martha (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Prairie Bird, pseud. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Pratt, Annies (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Rand, Ayn (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Randall, Margaret (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Resse, Elizabeth Phelps, Countess (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Richards, Laura (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Sachs, Emanie (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sampter, Jessie E. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sayers, Dorothy L.: letter to M. Nicolson (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Schreiner, Olive (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Sitwell, Edith (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Stein, Gertrude (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Stephens, Ann Sophia (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Sterling, Dorothy (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Stern, G.B.: letter to M. Nicolson (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Stowe, Harriet Beecher (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Susann, Jacqueline: Every Night, Josephine (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Swenson, May (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Teasdale, Sara (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Todd, Mabel Loomis (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Todd, Mary Ives (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Ward, Elizabeth Stuart (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Wells, Carolyn: verse (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Wharton, Edith Newbold (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Wheatley, Phillis (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Whitman, Walt: letter to Mary (Smith) Costelloe Berenson (photostat) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Wiggin, Kate Douglas (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Woolf, Virginia (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Zangwill, Israel (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Ziegler, Marianne (Box 7, Folder 15)
- SERIES IV. POETRY
  - General; poetry reviews (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  - Margaret Mitchell
    - General, [see also book on shelf]
      - University of Georgia Libraries: information on Mitchell collection (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Letter from Mildred Thompson to Margaret Storrs Grierson (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Smith College Libraries Annual Report: description of Mitchell Collection (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Clippings about Gone With the Wind (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Clippings about Margaret Mitchell (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Gone With the Wind: articles and pamphlets (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Smith College Scholarship Fund (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Photographs: Smith College, publicity, and miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence (to and from Margaret Mitchell)
      - Clark, Annetta and Mary 1936, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Dick, Jackson P. (including review of Gone With The Wind) 1937 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Draper, Jesse: letters written during WWII to friend, describing life in wartime Atlanta 1941-45 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
      - Dunn, Harris A. 1936 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Grierson, Margaret Storrs 1942 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Harris, Julia Collier 1936, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Harris, Julian 1936-37 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Thompson, Mildred 1937-38 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Plattner, Gladys (Lee) 1936, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Hill, Edith (Editor of Smith Alumnae Quarterly) 1936 (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Neely, Rachel S. 1907 (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Hungarian movie magazinecirca 1937 (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Rachel Schlesinger Neely to her daughter Rachel Neely Parker about Margaret Mitchell 1939 (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - Gone With the Wind (Motion Picture Edition) 1939 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Lorde, Audre: conversation between Audre Lorde and James Baldwin (orginally recorded for Essence magazine, December 1984 issue): audio recording, transcript, correspondence, and notes 1983 (Box 10)
    [Original audio tapes closed - use copies on CD]
- Books on Shelf
  - Anne Evans, Poems and Music 1880
  - Sarah Josepha Hale, Biography of Distinguished Women; Or, Woman's Record, From the Creation to A.D. 18691876
  - Margaret Mitchell Commemorative Stamps (US Post Office) 1986
  - Meredith Tax, ed. The Guarded Tongue2001 The Power of the Word2006> The Power of the Word II1996 Speaking in Tongues2002 The Spongue Set Free2002 A Women's World Bouquet1999